[Music]
Stanford
University all right so let me just tell
you a little uh bit about the origins of
string theory the origins of string
theory really were in hron physics they
did not have to do with quantum
gravity they had to do with protons
neutrons mesons particularly mesons in
fact the theory
was put forward at a time when it really
wasn't even known that uh for sure was
suspected but it wasn't known for sure
that protons and neutrons mesons and so
forth had a quark content to
them it was suspected that a Meson was a
pair of
quarks the idea of gluons did not yet
exist the idea of gluons well in fact it
actually did um but uh nobody paid too
much attention to it nembo had
postulated something like it but gluons
were not part of the standard discussion
of hadrons and let's say around 1969
19687 what was part of standard hyron
physics was one an interesting fact that
the number of particle
States was
large there was the
proton and the neutron of course I'm not
interested in the difference between
proton and neutron just think of them as
one thing the nucleon and then there was
another particle which was very similar
to the proton and neutron had a little
more Spin and a little bit heavier mass
and then there was another one above
that with a little bit heavier mass and
a little bit larger spin people drew
pictures diagrams they were called ch
frouchy flots flots not plots flots PL
plots
plots and they were diagrams which which
indicated the spectrum of objects like a
proton for example and they plotted uh
horizontally here let's see they plot
plotted vertically angular momentum and
horizontally the square of the mass who
decided to put the square of the mass
there instead of the
mass uh nobody the the diagrams had a
nicer look to them if you plotted Mass
squared and what was discovered
experimentally this is an experimental
FL fact getting getting my P's and my f
screwed up today an experimental fact
that the spectrum of particles okay
let's start with the uh let's start with
a proton that has half a unit of Spin
and a mass of one in certain units
namely the unit in which the mass of the
proton is one
that's approximately one
gev incidentally at that time the gev
didn't exist it was the
beev a billion now it's Giga okay and so
the proton and the neutron would were
over
here a mass of one mass square of one
and an angular momentum of a half then
there's another particle with angular
momentum three Hales these were firion
and so their angular momentum is
quantized in half integers and so there
was another one up here with a little
bit bigger Mass another one another one
and another one and rather remarkably
these particles all formed a straight
line a straight line in the uh in the
plot of L versus m now I should tell you
when Chu and fouchi first put this
forward the logic of drawing a straight
line you will only two points on this
plot and they thought it was a theorem
that through any two points you could
draw a straight line well it is a
theorem but uh these guys were not the
smartest uh well they were pretty smart
but
they they and so they said oh there's
two points let's draw a straight line
through them and miraculously as
experiment went on the additional
particles all landed on the same
line M squ in M squ yes they actually
said in M squ they they plotted it as a
function of M S and L and said two
points let's draw a straight line and
that worked out just fine but I mean
that explains why m s is the axis there
because they're hypothesizing L is
proportional M Square somehow they were
why were they why did they postulate
that instead of L proportional to
M they were
lucky they were lucky or else they had
some deep uh no it it wasn't
I'm it wasn't entirely luck and it
wasn't entirely and it wasn't a stupid
uh guess either there was some
interesting reasons for
it but the same pattern held true for
all hadrons or at least for all hyrons
that have been studied in detail for
example the
peson the peson also exists on a
trajectory these are known as re
trajectories re
gge for the uh for the Italian physic
this just Tulio
reg uh they're called reg trajectories
and if you plotted the Meson Spectrum
the Meson Spectrum mesons are bosons so
the angular momentto were integers for
example the P
Meson has almost zero Mass its mass
squared is even smaller than its mass
it's true in units of a
gev all right so the pone was almost
massless with almost zero angular
momentum and then there's the next one
up I forget what it's called
um uh I don't remember what the next one
is called I used to know but I don't
remember
anymore uh the next one up and the next
one up and five six seven particles
along a uh trajectory like
that the rzon which was another Meson
which starts with angular momentum
one also same pattern and what more all
of these trajectories were parallel to
each other they were parallel to each
other which said whatever this m² thing
is it takes exactly the same energy well
not exactly but approximately the same
energy to increase the M SAR by when you
to increase M squ when you increase the
angular momentum other words the
Spectrum was quantized of course it was
quantized these were particles and this
is quantum mechanics the Spectrum was
quantized but in each case the same
relationship between L and
M2 and the same Quantum jump in m^2 when
you increased L by one unit one unit now
means in units of pl's constant of
course so there's something going on
that was giving rise to large numbers of
particles of higher and higher angular
momentum higher angular momentum is not
that
uncommon you take a basketball you leave
it at rest that basketball has a certain
energy and therefore a certain mass and
you could plot it someplace and now you
spin the basketball give it one unit of
plunk angular momentum that's not easy
to do
incidently but when it has some angular
momentum it will be rotating it will
have some rotational energy so if you
increase its angular momentum by one
unit you will have to increase its
energy by a little bit tiny tiny bit for
a basketball and you can keep increasing
the angular momentum of the basketball
as you do so the energy will increase in
fact it will not look like a straight
line it will look like a
curve and it will end somewhere why does
the curve end the curve ends simply
because at some angular velocity the
centrifugal forces are so large that the
abask will just be torn AP part right so
it ends someplace at some high angular
momentum which represents uh you know
the strength of materials how how strong
is a whatever basketballs are made out
of so trajectories like that we're not
on usual you can plot them for atoms
atoms also have the property that as you
increase their angular momentum you
increase their ma their energy their
mass energy and mass being the same
thing but again for an atom uh there's
only so much mass you can give it before
you ionize the atom okay
so what was unusual particularly unusual
and again incidentally for atoms they
would not be straight
lines what was unusual here was the
Simplicity of the formula or the
Simplicity of the observation rather
straight lines I mean they were all
straight and parallel to each other
and um when you say parallel I me how
how do you mean I mean that if you were
to plot the Meson or the barion or the
proton or the neutron or the peson or
the
rzon its excited States would form the
same uh the same line in other words you
take a set of part A family of
particles same slope same slope and it
was called the universal re slope same
for bans and Fons same for different
families of uh of bans and fion now this
is strictly for those objects which are
hadrons those things made up out of
quarks and gluons which we now today
recognize as being made up of quarks and
gluons uh that was one observation the
implication of this observation was
fairly clear even though it was
misinterpreted at the time in many many
quarters uh it was fairly clear it said
that hadrons were composite that you
could spin them up this is not something
you can do with an electron there is no
excited state of an electron with higher
angular momentum at least not uh not the
within current experimental
bounds uh so electrons are like points
you can't you can't spin a point uh
spinning a point doesn't mean anything
turning a point point you can spin a
lump so somehow these objects
were not simple Point particles that was
the message that should have been and in
many quarters was taken from
this and in fact that they had a stretch
ability that
uh from this picture you could deduce if
you wanted and we will we will you could
deduce the fact that they deform as they
spin you wouldn't it's not obvious from
here but you can all right but there was
something else there was another
observation which was a very bizarre OB
observation let me describe it to you in
terms of Meson Meson
scattering let's take Meson Meson and
for particular let's take peson peson
scattering here's a Pion coming in a
peson it's called Pi doesn't matter
whether it's pi+ Pi minus doesn't matter
and it scatters off another pi mizon
there is a particle called the
razon which while it's not a composite
of two P
mesons two P mesons can come together at
a vertex and a fan diagram and make a
rzon let's make the rzon like that we're
going to talk we may or may not talk
more about these mesons it's not
important that the the idea is important
but the particular names are not
important rzon and then that
Pyon could uh then that rzon could
materialize as a pair of peson again
this being a Fineman diagram
conventional Fineman diagram and it
would govern the properties of Pon Pion
scattering
probabilities okay that was the first
thing now these are all pons
here any Quantum field theorist would
immediately tell you if you have this
diagram here where the two P come in
this way and make a rzon and then go off
as two pons there will be another
diagram which looks like this it's just
the same diagram turned on its
side where a
rzon is exchanged between two peson in
this case a rzon jumps from here to here
and this without the pons ever
annihilating but this is just the same
diagram turned on its side and if one
exists the other has to exist that's a
consequence of principles of quantum
field
Theory so that's something that uh that
everybody believed but then once it was
recognized that this rzon was
not a unique creature but came along
with this whole family this whole regit
trajectory of excited state
it became clear that there was no reason
to only have AR rzon in here you could
add together all the various you could
add P mesons come in form not the rzon
but the next excited state of the rzon
or the next excited state of the rzon
and so actually when you draw this
diagram you're really committed to
adding up the contribution of
all the mesons along here
likewise here if you can exchange a
razon you can also exchange all the
excited
States well there was something very
very suspicious very very peculiar when
people numerically went to do this they
actually added up from known
experimental data the contributions of
the rzon the row Prime Meson the row
double Prime Meson and so forth and so
on they did that
and they did the same thing for the
exchange of the razon and they found
something rather
remarkable they found that to some
approximation the sum of all the rzon
going this way gave rise to about the
same thing as the sum over all the rzon
and its Partners going in the opposite
in the in the other channel it was
called okay in other words it appeared
to be
overcounting all you needed to repr
represent the data and all that you
needed to represent the the the physics
of Pi Pi scattering was summing over row
row Prime row double Prime in this
Annihilation process Annihilation and
Recreation process and in fact you
didn't need to add this in because this
already seemed to contain it numerically
numerically on the other hand it was
also true that you could ignore this all
together and add all all this up and
again get the right answer answer get
something which looked pretty much like
experimental data that was very peculiar
any Quantum field theorist would look at
this and say complete how rubbish you
you you if you have this you have to add
that you have to add it you don't uh you
don't get to say it's this or this you
get to say it's this and this okay but
peculiarly when you added up all these
contributions it simply gave you for
free the effects of another diagram here
for that reason I and other people began
to draw
diagrams which looked not so much like
findan diagrams but which looked more
like
this we didn't know what we were doing
we're just saying look something's going
on here first of all we had the idea
that there were quirks quirks were not a
new idea and we said what must be going
on is there must be a picture which
looks something like
this replacing the Fineman
diagram this would be a quark this would
be an an anti- Quark this would be a
quark going this way an anti- Quark
going this way and likewise over
here we drew diagrams like that now it
took some time for us to think about
filling in what goes on in here we just
drew pictures like this and we said look
at this if
you think about somehow what's going on
has a topology let's call it a topology
which looks like this then look if you
cut it this way if you imagine slicing
it in an instant of time time is running
upward of course in
all uh in
all pictures Fineman diagrams time we're
allowing to run upward if you slice this
right through the middle then you see
something that looks
like a Fineman diagram in which two
particles come together and join and
make another D particle if we think of
particles there pairs of qus then this
figure
here can
represent a picture like this on the
other hand if we take that same picture
and slice it this way it looks like a
picture in which something is jumping
across slice it the other way it looks
like these two
particles
produced a thing which jumped from the
side to the side so this was kind of the
origin
of pictures one more ingredient was
added it was just added for
fun just just a curious a curious
question if there are these quirks
what's holding those quirks together
well maybe it's something in here these
are SpaceTime diagrams of course maybe
something is BR in between the
quarks and if
so then when you slice through these
diagrams then what you would see is two
quarks with something bridging between
them and that something of course would
have the structure of something
onedimensional connecting a quark and an
anti- Quark a
string and a pair of
quirks if you cut it the other way
that same two-dimensional sheet here
could be sliced into a picture where a
string was exchanged from one side to
another this was the very crude origins
of the idea of string
theory in fact it isn't exactly where it
came from but it could have it did to
some extent different people thought of
it at different
ways um
so
what's more what's more once a hron is a
string with two quirks connected to it
you can spin it something you can't do
to an electron you can spin it you can
try to calculate with some assumptions
about the nature of the material forming
the string its elasticity it's its
various properties you can start asking
how the energy of it what kind of energy
is there incidentally first of all is
kinetic energy and second of all is
stretching energy so with some kind of
assumptions about the nature of uh these
strings or this uh material in here you
can start asking questions about how the
energy increases as a function of the
angular
momentum surprisingly with a relatively
simple assumption that we're going to do
and we may get to it today I hope we get
it to it to it
today uh we'll see
that these pictures are not as arbitrary
as they might seem L versus m² or linear
function of L versus m^2 is exactly what
you need now I yeah why did you suggest
that it was something like a string
something new rather than a normal
particle exchange between the two qus
that's how you well this is not a this
is not a particle exchange this is
something that's sitting there all the
points of it between the uh between the
quirks this
is if you were to slice it at an
instant other words take a look at it at
an instant here it is at an instant it
consists of a quark an anti- quark and a
whole bunch of stuff in between now that
bunch of stuff in between might have
been a collection of particles that are
forming a string you know that are
forming a string-- like thing
they might uh no no Prejudice about
whether it was truly continuous or
whether it was just something which was
approximating something continuous in
between but there was one thing that
made you think there might be something
more fundamental about it than just a
shoelace and that was that as far as we
could tell these trajectories didn't end
if you take a shoelace and put a pair of
golf balls at the opposite ends of it
and spin it around eventually you'll
come to the point where
breaks and as far as could be told these
regid trajectories did not break so it
seemed maybe that uh there was something
uh new going on yeah can the standard
model accurately described Pon
scattering
uh to the extent that the standard model
gives rise to a string like Behavior it
can
um yeah the standard model can describe
a great deal about Pion scattering these
days yeah depending on the energy at
very low
energies the standard model has a very
good description of Pon scattering as
the energy goes up where you start
getting into the issues of these
particles being exchanged back and
forth the standard model begins to get a
little bit more difficult to deal with
and a string-- like picture becomes uh
becomes uh more
useful no how did they know that the
trajectory does not end no of course not
no
no no but didn't give any sign of giving
out
and uh so what that meant what it
appeared is this thing could be
stretched more or less indefinitely
without much happening to it
we'll we'll come back to this
point well in fact they're not entirely
different than gluons in some sense they
may be collections of gluons in fact
they have to be collections of
gluons the present understanding of it
today is something like this that um
that the gluon field is like the Maxwell
field all right uh the
quirks you asked me about bar magnets
okay so the quirks are like poles of the
uh North Pole and South Pole of a bar
magnet North Pole South Pole you can't
have monopoles the only way you can have
a North Pole or South pole is to have it
as the end of a bar
magnet okay or you could say it a
different
way you can have dipoles you can have
magnetic fields which like
this here it looks
like there a magnetic monopole lines of
flux spreading out here it looks like
there are lines of flux spreading out
and there might be some reason why the
lines of flux form a narrow tube in
between the current understanding of the
connection
between gluons and these strings go
something like this Quantum mechanic
Fields can be described as either
particles or
Fields let's take the field description
in the field description the gluon field
between two
quarks no quark and an
antiquark would be like the field
configuration between a particle between
a charge and an opposite charge it would
look like
this
that's what the field between a positive
charge and a negative charge looks like
the energy as you separate them is the
energy stored in the field in between
now for ordinary electrodynamics those
field lines spread out and because they
spread out the field diminishes in
between them as you separate the field
as you separate the part the
charges the field lines spread out the
field diminishes in between and that's
the usual pattern our understanding
today is that the nonlinearities we've
talked about this before but I'll just
mention it again that the nonlinearities
in Quantum chromodynamics have the
effect of causing these field lines to
attract in a certain way and the effect
of it is that the field lines form
strings that look like that as you pull
these apart the string doesn't spread
this way it just gets longer and longer
and longer that's our current
understanding and if you like it's
permissible to think of the string as
being made up out of
gluons as you pull it apart it's not
like a shoelace or a rubber band as you
stretch a rubber band the number of
molecules in it doesn't
change the number of molecules in it and
they just stretch and eventually because
the number of molecules doesn't change
eventually they get too far from each
other and bang the rubber band breaks
but imagine a rubber band in which as
you stretched it
every time there was a gap opening up
between atoms a new atom was inserted in
between in that case you could imagine
that you could stretch this uh ad infin
item forever without breaking
it
and that's the nature of the gluon field
between a quark and an antiquark as you
stretch it the energy of stretching goes
into creating more gluons in between
Cen and you can just stretch the hell
out of that uh that system and it won't
break yeah can you extend that analogy
to say that the string that makes up say
an electron is somehow composed of blons
as well it's composed well first of all
we don't know that string that electrons
really are made of
strings
no no th this all of this physics was
taking place on a length
scale of the size of a
proton this is an enormous length scale
by comparison with the scales of uh of
quantum gravity which take place at the
plunk length it's a more or less perhaps
accidental fact that um that the
mathematics of string theory has
described both things they're quite
different they occur at completely
different length scales
but through these
considerations I other people began to
work out the
mathematics of interacting
strings can you really quantify this can
you really make uh a theory of
interacting strings which will give you
uh all of the physics of the interacting
hadrons the answer at the time is you
looked it looked promising it kept it
looked very promising in fact it kept
promising and promising and promising
like string theory today uh huge promise
but never quite did it right okay for
reasons that in
hindsight are fairly
clear the precise mathematics that we
were using was not quite the right
mathematics for studying hyrons it was
the right mathematics for studying
quantum gravity it and so we kept
getting as much as we didn't want it we
kept getting particles in the theory
with zero mass and spin 2 what is
that a graviton nobody wanted a graviton
this was a nuisance go away graviton we
couldn't make it go away nothing we
could do could make it go
away and eventually some smart guy named
John Schwarz and Joel shark and said
wait a minute wait a minute may maybe
we're being dumb maybe this is a theory
of quantum graph and not a not a theory
of
hadrons incidentally string theory of
hadrons finally has been put together
with a proper mathematics it does work
but it's a little bit
different okay let's talk
about well
okay before talking about
um strings the mathematics of
strings let's talk about about
relativity versus non-relativistic uh
kinematics coincidentally just a
buzzword this two-dimensional structure
in here which is what is it it's
replacing the idea of a world
line a world line is being replaced by a
two-dimensional
sheet such a sheet I think the term
actually goes back to me was called a
world sheet today it's the standard
terminology
uh so strings are world sheets looked at
at an instant in the same sense that
particles are World lines looked at at
an
instant so that's the uh that's the
jargon world sheets and World lines sir
can I go back to that
diagram uh okay be that there's a string
in there with as it stretch isn't that
put the gluons in tension no
and so how do you get from a plus to
minus well the lines of flux come out
one side and go in the other
side same way you go from a North Pole
to a South Pole in a
magnet not any magnet any magnet has two
poles there's always two poles of
opposite sign no magnet has two North
Poles no magnet has two South Poles
every magnet has one North Pole and one
South Pole north and south like plus and
minus is there a wall in there a what is
there a wall in there a black
wall I don't know what a black wall
is despite the fact that I'm the Felix
BL professor of physics I don't
know yeah could this stream be
considered either continuous or discrete
or does it make any difference in this
well you see now you now you're running
into the subtleties of quantum
mechanics is the electromagnetic field a
Continuum well in some ways yes is the
electromagnetic field made of discrete
Quant yes in some way
yes uh and
um quantum mechanics tells you that uh
that that distinction between Continuum
and discret is a very subtle
one uh and I won't try to answer it uh
right
now I think both are true it's Continuum
and it's discreet depending on the way
you think about
it all right next
question
um non nonrelativistic versus
relativistic kinematics or kinematics or
simple ideas about uh particles energy
momentum the symmetries of uh of motion
of
on the face of it relativistic and
non-relativistic physics look very very
different of course we know that they're
connected to each other but let's uh
let's uh quantify or discuss that
difference yes yes Michael you can
always ask your
question as long as you keep bringing me
cookies string being uh
a a point in time at the uh um P the uh
the world sheet yeah okay uh if you
change the angle of that cross-section
of space time do you still describe what
you get as something like a string yes
yes the lorence transformation of a what
you're talking about is lorence
transformation of course the lorence
transformation is a is a is a moving
string but it's still a string
absolutely right so if you were to
consider a frame in which simultaneity
was this line here you would still be
seeing a string but you would be seeing
a string in
motion as opposed to standing
still uh right when I say standing still
incidentally I mean the center of mass
of it standing still strings wiggle a
lot they've got a lot of tension and
they vibrate a lot so they don't stand
still but the center of mass can stand
still all right let's come now to the
issue of Relativity versus non-
relativity how do you describe a
relativistic string well that's awfully
complicated describing anything
relativistically is complicated for
example just the let's begin with the
energy of a particle the energy of a
particle
nonrelativistically Point particle is p^
2 over 2 m momentum squared if
the uh depending on the number of
Dimensions we would have to add up the
various components of momentum divided
by twice the mass that's a nice simple
algebraic quantity the square of a
function is easy to compute and so forth
uh you might add to this a constant and
the constant you would think of as The
Binding energy or just the energy of the
particle because it's there so you might
put something else there let's called it
B the energy that it takes to assemble a
particle whatever it is the
characteristic of it is that it does not
depend on the state of motion it doesn't
depend on
p uh in a relativistic theory there's a
natural candidate for what this B is
it's the energy of a thing when p is
equal to zero right I mean relativity or
not relativity it's the energy of the
particle at
rest what is uh what are we uh in a
special theory of relativity what do we
put there MC squ of course so there's a
natural thing to put there which would
be MC squ but let's just think of it as
a additive constant and it's constant
only in so far as it does not depend on
P it might vary from different kind of
particle to different kind of
particle it could be the binding energy
holding together an atom it could be
whatever but it doesn't depend on the uh
overall motion and for many purposes you
can just drop this because it's always
there and uh it doesn't uh energy
differences don't depend on it so p^2
over 2 m
and p^2 over 2m is terribly easy to
manipulate it's just a thing that you uh
it's just
quadratic uh of
course if you have many particles in a
system then what you do is you add up
the energy if they're not interacting
and you also add up the internal binding
energy internal energy you could call it
you add them all up again this doesn't
matter because energy differences don't
uh are insensitive to it
now how do we get this from relativity
let's remind ourselves what the formula
for the energy of a particle is the
energy of a particle this is
e all right in relativity it's equal to
the square root of P ^2 +
m^2 it's of course the I'm going to
correct this in a minute but it's of
course equal to the sum of all the
particles let's just write it as E
equals the sum of all all the particles
in the system of P ^2 + m^2 where p^2 is
px2 + p y^2 + pz S or however many
dimensions we wish to take into
account well why take into account
however many dimensions are appropriate
to the problem so this would be pi and
Mi for the I particle and also X Y and Z
and whatever else okay how do we go from
here to here well first of all I left
something out I left out C to the 4th
that's the fourth power of the speed of
light and m² m s c^2 here as soon as I
finish this one little demonstration I'm
going to set c equal to
one maybe four and two are switch Yeah
four and two a
switch uh do I have it wrong you're
right sorry MC s yeah C to the 4th very
good c^ 2 p^2 c^ 2 m^2 C to 4th good
boy I would have been in
trouble
okay the non-relativistic
limit is appropriate for problems where
a particle is moving very slowly which
means its momentum is very small and in
particular in which p^2 c^2 is much
smaller than m^2 C 4 under those
circumstances you can take theare root
of p^2 + m^2 and write it first in the
form uh m^2 C 4 * 1 + p ^ 2 c^2 over n^2
C
4 you can factor out of the square root
the m^2 C to 4th and that gives you mc^
2 on the outside that's a good
sign but with a correction and the
correction is this over here what do you
do with it you expand out the square
root you use the formula that the square
root of 1 plus a small quantity is 1
plus the small quantity divided by two
square T of 1 plus a small quantity is
equal to the 1 plus the small quantity
over
two that's an approximation of course
it's not
exact but as the small quantity gets
smaller and smaller it becomes better
and better so what do you get you get MC
squar
plus p^ 2 c^2 over m c^
2 MC to 4th / 2 all time MC mc^ 2
here okay so let's see what cancel MC
squ that's familiar that's the
relativistic rest energy but this here
has four powers of C in the numerator
four powers of C in the
denominator C goes
away it has one power of M in the
numerator two powers of M in the
denominator cancel them and you get the
good
old non-relativistic formula but it's an
approximation it's an
approximation and when is it
good it's good when all particles are
moving
slowly uh it's not just the whole system
which has to be moving slowly to use
non-relativistic physics you might for
example have a box of particles and the
Box may be moving
slowly but inside the Box the particles
may be moving with close to the speed of
light you cannot use pure
non-relativistic physics for all of
these
particles
uh because they have relative motions
which are up near the speed of light so
strictly speaking the n relativistic
limit is a good thing to do when all of
the particles are moving slowly and it
is an
approximation now there's another sense
in which non-relativistic
physics is an exact description of
relativistic physics so I'm going to
show you this this is something that
goes back a long ways in particle
physics uh when I worked on it in
1968 or 67 or sometime was called the
infinite momentum frame now it's called
a l cone frame so if you look up a l
cone frame you will see these things uh
described okay but it's it's easy it's
easy if I don't want to do it in Great
in enormous generality it's easy and
here's what the trick is instead
of thinking of a system in its rest
frame when we said or near the rest
frame in other words a frame in which
every momentum is slow we're going to do
a different trick we're going to look at
it from the point of view of a frame
where everything the entire system has
been boosted up to have huge momentum
along one
axis in other words boost it up so that
it's moving down the z-axis let's take
that to be the z-axis so that it has
humongously large momentum along the
z-axis there's no loss in generality
there we can take any system
and just boost it so that it's along the
z-axis and then rewrite what this
formula looks like okay so I'm going to
you know I'm going to do I'm going to
set c equal to one now I'm not going to
bother keeping C the energy is the sum
of all the particles of again squ < TK
of p^2 +
m^2 which is equal to square < TK of p
z^ 2 plus PX x^2 + P y^
2+
m^2 but now we're boosting the hell out
of the system along the
z-axis until every single particle has a
huge momentum along the z-axis every
single one of them if there's any
particle which is going backward on the
z-axis you just haven't boosted it
enough just boost it more until it's
going forward with a large
momentum in that case all of the pzs are
very large what happens to PX py and M
when you boost
something nothing that's the rest
Mass we don't even speak about moving
Mass anymore the rest mass and the
components of momentum perpendicular to
the Boost don't change when you boost
something okay so now the big quantity
is pz and PX py and M are kept fixed and
are much smaller than p Z so the
appropriate thing to do here in taking
the limit is expand it for large pz
expand it for this being small a way to
do that is to write this in the
form square root of 1 plus let's just
call it p² uh PX well let's write it out
px2 + P y^
2+
m^2 / pz ^ 2 all
times pz on the outside
right pz on the outside if I brought the
pz inside the square root it would have
to be squared it would be pz squared and
then it would cancel this pz squ
here okay what's the next
step expand use the binomial expansion
the binomial approximation to do exactly
the same thing we did over
here this is now the small quantity
and so this becomes
pz * 1 + px2 + p y^ 2 +
m^2 over twice p
z twice pz squar excuse me pz
squared or to summarize it all the
energy
is the sum over all the particles of pz
of the I
particle plus the sum of let's call it p
uh P will now stand for PX and py let's
use Little P Little P stands for PX and
py Little
P Squared over twice big pz
plus m^2 over T big
pz
no
no it was a pz up here and a pz squar
down here okay
good I don't need to put brackets
in okay first
observation if we believe in momentum
conservation which we do in this class
if we believe in momentum
conservation then first of all this is
just the total momentum of the system
the first term here is the total Z
component of momentum going down the
z-axis it's
huge very
large but it's a constant it's a
constant and as various things go on in
this system the total momentum never
changes if you have a constant term in
the energy which doesn't change in any
way during the course of a uh know a
constant additive
thing adding it to the energy or
subtracting it from the energy doesn't
do anything for example if you added the
electric charge to the
energy since electric charge is
conserved and the only thing that's ever
important in physics is differences of
energy you could just drop it or keep it
it doesn't matter the same is true here
you have a a conserved quantity which is
conserved for other reasons than energy
conservation energy of course is also
conserved but pz is concerned for other
reasons here's something which never
changes you can just drop it if you were
to think of the energy as being the
hamiltonian of a system it would make no
difference whether you whether you drop
it or don't drop it because it's a
conserved quantity which never changes
so you can drop
this will make no difference the rest of
the energy here is this thing here now
first of all notice that pz is in the
denominator what does that mean why is
there why is the energy so small in
particular energy
differences for example differences
depending on the state of motion in the
XY plane they will be tiny why are they
tiny anybody
know why are the energy different okay I
I will tell you for this it's useful to
remember a bit of quantum mechanics even
though we don't need to be doing quantum
mechanics what is the meaning of the
energy the energy of course in quantum
mechanics is the same as the
hamiltonian it is also in classical
mechanics but what's the meaning of the
hamiltonian in quantum mechanics do you
remember your quantum
mechanics operator it is an operator
operator it's a Herm Mission operator
but it's also the
oper it's an I value of the energy but
it's also associated with something else
it's also associated with time
Evolution all right remember that this
is the same as i d by
DT namely i h bar probably d by
DT this is its action as an operator on
a state
that what it means to say energies are
very small is that systems are changing
very slowly this is also true
incidentally In classical mechanics I
just uh point this out quantum mechanics
if the energies of a system are very
very small it means changes take place
very very
slowly the smaller the energy if the
energy scales uh with some 1 over pz
here it means that the larger that pz is
the slower things take place in the
system what's going on here very simple
it's time dilation the more you boost
the system up to higher and higher
momentum in your reference frame the
slower things take
place okay that's interesting but of
course we have all the time in the
world uh a system moving we can wait as
long as we like to see things take place
if we're trying to make a theory of
radioactive decay sure boosting it up
will make the radioactive decay go
slower but uh we can rescale that out we
can say instead of working on a scale of
uh micros seconds we'll work on a scale
of millions of years and we'll also see
the uh we'll also see the
um uh the nucleus Decay everything just
has to be rescaled so this one over pz
there the total this is the one over pz
this is incidentally for the I particle
and we add them all
up so the fact that all the pzs get
large incidentally in fixed proportion
they all get large in fixed
proportion that said the energy got
small that's a completely expected
phenomenon apart from that if we
rescale only
pzs ignore the fact that they get big or
just rescale the evolution of the system
this hamiltonian or this expression for
energy really does look like the
non-relativistic non-relativistic
expression with respect to the motion in
the XY
plane for the motion in the XY plane the
energy is proportional to the square of
the XY
momentum just as it is for the
non-relativistic
particle but notice that the
role of the mass of the
particle in this non-relativistic
analogy is not the rest
Mass it's the momentum along the z-axis
what this means what is mass mass is
inertia right that got to do with the
difficulty of deflecting something uh
what this is saying is that the momentum
along the
z-axis is functioning as a kind of
inertia with respect to forces in the
perpendicular Direction and the whole
thing is looking very very much like uh
if we think of pz as a constant then all
this is is the non-relativistic
formula for the energy of a
two-dimensional particle now notice we
now have only two dimensions of
motion and what is what about this term
over here what how we should we
interpret that again remember that we
think of pz as being independent of the
state of Mo
at least a two-dimensional motion so
with respect to this two-dimensional
analogy analogy between relativistic and
non-relativistic physics it's an analogy
between relativistic physics and
two-dimensional Motion in which pz plays
the role of the mass and how about this
object over
here it plays the role of The Binding
energy does it have the right properties
to be a binding energy the only thing
about a binding energy is that it should
be independent of the state of motion it
should not depend
on this does not depend on the
two-dimensional motion so this is kind
of interesting and it's not only
interesting it's incredibly useful in
studying particle Dynamics and
absolutely
Central to uh to studying
strings is
that in a very precise and exact way
the motion of a relativistic system when
it's boosted up to enormously large
momentum behaves completely
nonrelativistically with respect to the
motion in the plane perpendicular to the
uh to the
Boost okay it's for this reason that
string theory is also
often uh described in terms of
mathematics which is the mathematics of
a non-relativistic
string a nonrelativistic string a
non-relativistic string is a collection
of Point
particles uh in some limit in which you
let the point particles get more and
more
continuous all moving
nonrelativistically Why by what hutzpah
do we uh do we use non-relativistic
physics to describe anything as
complicated as a relativistic uh string
well the answer is that in the infinite
momentum frame which these days is
called the light cone frame mostly
because it has nothing to do with
cones nothing whatever to do with
cones uh I'll tell you another time
where it's called a light cone frame not
important but in the infinite momentum
frame motion is non relativistic and you
have a chance that perhaps the motion of
a string when it's boosted up may be
described by by a kind of
non-relativistic quantum mechanics and
this seems to be borne out not seems to
be this has been uh the techniques that
have been used for since the very
beginning of string theory to analyze
relativistic
strings
um let me show you the simplest fact
yeah uh no okay let me show you one of
the very simple
connections uh that um that follow from
thinking this way let's now hypothesize
or
postulate that we can think of particles
as
strings using the two dimens using the
two-dimensional analogy with
non-relativistic physics to explore
those strings as if they were
conventional non-relativistic not
shoelaces but something closer to rubber
bands
stretchable uh they can move they can
flap they can do all the things that a
rubber band an ideal rubber band can do
[Music]
uh What uh what's the mathematical
description of a two Dimension a rubber
band which is moving around in two
Dimensions let's take our rubber band to
be an open rubber band that means
somebody took a scissor cut it and uh
opened it up let's begin with open
strings open strings mean strings with
two ends there may or may not be
something interesting attached to the
ends but we're interested more in the
strings
um let's write the physics of a uh of a
string what is the what is the energy
what is the energy stored in a string
all right we can think of the string as
a collection of
points Point particles which later on we
will take
limits one of the things we will do when
we take a limit is we'll let the mass of
each point go to zero that's because
we're going to have an the whole string
has a has a finite Mass we're going to
think of it as being a collection of a
virtual Infinity of Point masses it had
better be that in taking the limit we
let the mass of each point go to zero
all right but what's uh what's the
energy of this the energy is going to be
proportional the kinetic energy it'll be
the sum of all the points
of X I do
sared these are two dimensional now so
we could write this as X + Y do^
2 that's the I point divided by
two and we might put here in a mass of
the I particle which later on we're
going to let go to zero but let's let's
not be too uh I'll just tell you how to
do the the Continuum limit I'll show you
how to do it I'll just tell you how to
do it all right what are we missing out
of this
formula inter inter directions yeah uh
these points are attracting each other
if they weren't attracting each other
they would just fly apart they're
forming a string they are in addition to
the points we have to put in the little
springs that connect
them so think of it as a chain of little
balls and little Springs can you see the
springs
all right little balls and little
Springs
um let's just call this x of i^ s x of
i^ 2 now stands for X x² x do2 + y do
squ okay what is the potential energy
between the points the potential energy
is a sum also over all neighboring
pairs so there's another sum of I
here there's a spring constant let's
just call it K all the mass points have
the same mass there's a spring constant
there and what is the potential energy
between a pair of points it'll be
proportional to the distance between
them x i - x i +
squared probably a two
there this is Hook's law
this is hooks law the energy stored in a
stretched spring is proportional to the
distance of stretching
squared that's the hooks law uh formula
for
the now what happens when you go to the
Continuum limit in other words you let
the points get denser and denser and
denser more and more of them you have to
do two things you have to let the mass
of each one go to zero and
you have to also let the spring constant
what it is you want the spring constant
to get big or
small
big big can you you know why supposing
you take a rubber band and you take a
rubber band uh a big long piece of
rubber band and you stretch it it's easy
to stretch now take two points very
close to each other and try to stretch
them that same distance much harder okay
so the spring constant gets big and the
mass gets small but in the end what you
get just take it from me what you get is
of course an integral represent uh uh an
integral replacing the
sum the integral is over a parameter
along the
string you have to introduce a
mathematical parameter along the string
we can call that parameter we'll give it
a name
Sigma Sigma goes from one end of the
string where we can arbitrarily say it's
zero
so Sigma is zero at this end and at the
other end we can arbitrarily say Sigma
is equal to
Pi I could have taken it to be one I
could have taken it to be seven it
doesn't
matter
uh it will be useful to think to call it
Pi the reason is later on we're going to
study closed strings which go all the
ways around in a loop and it's nice to
say they go from zero to 2 pi that's all
but uh they go from 0 to Pi so this sum
over the mass points is going to be an
integral from 0 to Pi D Sigma this is
adding them all up and we're going to
have the kinetic
energy
of the little element of string at Point
Sigma continuous string now we take a
little element at Point Sigma we take it
velocity squared divide by
two and what about this term over
here uh i' I've I've chosen the mass to
go in the appropriate way I'm dropping
the mass here by the time you finished
um you can absorb the mass into
something else doesn't matter what it's
just X do squ it's clearly kinetic
energy all right what about this term
here what's that going to look like how
about x i - x i + 1 what you replace
that with
derivative derivative this is
like the derivative of x with respect to
Sigma
squared so the other term here will be
derivative of x with respect to Sigma
this is derivative of x with respect to
time this is derivative of x with
respect to Sigma
squared this is the energy of the string
if I wanted to write the lran you all
remember what a lran is energy is
kinetic energy plus potential energy
lran is kinetic
energy minus so if I wanted the
lran it would be
this if I wanted the energy it would be
with a plus
sign okay I'll write the energy we'll
write the
energy
hamiltonian
plus let's focus for a little bit I'm
going to stop in a few minutes and uh
and uh we'll take a rest but let's focus
a little bit on a
string which happens to have no overall
Center of mass Motion in the two
dimensions in the XY plane we're coming
back back now to
here what we're going to do is use a
model for a relativistic
string which is simply based on this
kind of infinite momentum thinking but
in which there are only two x's the two
x's moving in the uh in the direction
perpendicular to the motion so this
could be called X and Y but I'll just
call it X do s it really consists of X
do s+ y do s this one consists of the X
by the sigma plus DX plus Dy by D Sigma
s is that clear yeah
okay oh I just absorbed it I just chose
oh sorry there is a two two is
important uh I chose K in such a way to
make sure that when I got to the final
Continuum limit the coefficient was one
remember it's something that has to that
has to vary as you vary the spacing and
uh it can be chosen
uh in such a way as to make this
uh and this is the conventional energy
of a vibrating string it has two terms
kinetic and potential potential
proportional to the stretching this is
this the XD Sigma is the stretching of
the
string okay I want to point out one
interesting
fact this Hamilton here or this
expression for energy is the
generalization of this expression
here for a system of particles which
also has a interaction between them but
the whole thing the whole
object it may be vibrating and doing
things but the whole object is an object
we can call it a particle who's to say
it's not a
particle
uh uh protons and neutrons have spin
they rotate there's all sorts of
internal motions in particles we know
there are internal motions of particles
internal motions of atoms internal
motions of quirks inside protons and
neutrons uh the best bet would be there
are all sorts of internal motions in
every particle so this stringy
vibrations and internal motions and so
forth that perhaps not perhaps but would
add up to all the internal Motion in the
particle all the internal energy in the
particle the internal energy would be
the contributions to the energy from the
potential stretching and from the
relative motion of the different parts
the overall motion we'll separate that
out soon enough but the overall motion
of the string the center of mass of it
that would just be treated as the as the
position of the particle but the
relative stretching and the relative
vibration that's internal
energy so when we calculate the internal
energy of this particle what should we
relate it to we should relate it not to
the mass but to the mass
squared in this correspondence it's not
an analogy it's an
exact statement about the properties of
uh
relativity is a very precise
mathematical statement which I won't
make now but there was a there was an
exact sense in which fast moving systems
are completely relative non-relativistic
in the two-dimensional sense what would
the internal energy correspond to it
would correspond not to the mass of the
particle but to the mass
squared so for for a string at rest
think of a string which has no Motion in
the uh in the XY plane all it's doing is
vibrating and it has internal energy
that internal energy has to be
identified with the square of the mass
of the entire assembly of constituents
of the
string if the constituents of the string
are adding up to something that we want
to call a
particle then that particle has a mass
squared which is the sum of all of the
internal energies in inside the particle
now this is an interesting fact we get
Mass squared for the energy of a
particle in this
framework there are some C's around
which I haven't tried to keep track
of yeah there's C's and yeah there's C's
and uh right uh yeah I haven't tried to
keep track of of them
but this connection was something I knew
that nobody else knew at the
time I worked on both these things uh
and um
so this is interesting this is exciting
another fact another fact is that a
string is not so different than a spring
if you look at the Spectrum of energies
of a
string it's quantized in pretty much the
same way we'll come we're going to do
the quantization of it carefully but
the basic fact about the quantization of
it is the string is a collection of
Springs and springs have quantized
energy and what's the formula for the
energy of a quantum mechanical
oscillator an integer multiple of
something each time you you increase the
energy of a spring or a string the
internal energy by one unit it increases
the mass squared by one
unit increases the mass squared by one
unit quick question yeah the m m energy
is m s the m is this where simple
confusion is M the mass of the string
yeah it's the mass of the whole string
the whole string the whole string and
the energy so she double the size the
mass of the string be four
times because m s would be is that
correct yeah yeah you you you stolen my
thunder well
I all right
confused okay but now well okay let's
let's look at this formula a little bit
carefully now and see if we can see
anything
interesting quick question yeah
um right side you have m² there that
would kind of kind of connote the rest
mass of the system
correct it is in fact the rest mass of
the string in a frame of reference where
it's not zipping along but where it was
really stationary but the equation seems
to be seem to be not uh well describing
a photon it well that's right because a
photon is
massless well that just corresponds to m
equals z on the right hand side and
you're going to ask me how can this
thing be zero well we're going to come
to that that is a very significant and
interesting point we're going to come to
it for the moment it's just the mass of
the entire
string the entire including its internal
energy including its stretching energy
all of the energies that you would
normally add up to find MC squ to find
the rest Mass that's what this is here
okay it's just a before we go this is
just a classical mechanics and
relativity applied so far we haven't
invented any other we haven't ined Quant
mechanics yet do things like that no
okay but if we did introduce quantum
mechanics we would know that this string
would be would have quantized energy
levels and therefore quantized Mass
squares right in fact if we increase the
angular momentum by one
Quantum then the quantized energy the
Quantum of energy that would be
introduced would be a Quantum of m s not
a Quantum of
M right
so right right this was an immediate
piece of evidence that uh that moreover
yeah okay this was this was one of the
hints that uh one of the hints there's
another interesting fact here um
supposing you took a string which was
not moving but which you stretched out
but you stretched out to a certain
length Okay how much energy would would
it have well then all of its energy
would be potential energy not kinetic
energy let's calculate what it would be
how big is the XD Sigma well if you
stretch that out
uniformly then the change in X along the
length of it would just be the length of
the string L would just be we stretching
it out to a physical distance
L we stretch it out to a physical
distance
L over a distance from zero to PI
right all right so the derivative of x
with respect to Sigma would be something
like L / Pi I don't care about the pies
right now they're not what's what's
interesting DX by D Sigma would just be
proportional to the length of the
string okay if you stretched It Out by
distance L and divided by the range of
Sigma from 0 to Pi that would give you
DX by D Sigma and so we can say that the
X by the sigma is proportional to the
length of the string and the X by the
sigma squar would just be the square of
the length of the string right this is
Hook's
law this is Hook's law for a string if
you stretch it out the distance L the
energy stored in it
nonrelativistically will be l s but
that's what has to equal the mass
squared now we know something
interesting about how how about the
energetics of the string if we were to
study it in the rest frame in the rest
frame of the string the energy of the
string is the
mass we got from Mass to mass squared by
boosting the string but if we went back
now and we said look wait a minute we
know eal
mc^2 that's rest Mass what is the rest
mass of the string and the answer is
that the rest
mass is proportional to this is a
proportionality Factor proportional to
its
length in other words this string has
the property that the energy if you
think about it in its rest
frame if you stretch it out the distance
L it will have an energy which will grow
with L and be proportional to
L in the rest frame it doesn't look like
a hooks law string at all it looks like
a different kind of string whose energy
is proportional to its
length well that's very interesting
because it fits with another picture it
fits with the picture which I described
before
of lines of flux connecting quarks and
anti-
quarks lines of flux would
produce I slice them through like this
this they would produce a patch of
electric or magnetic field here it
doesn't matter whether it's electric or
magnetic lines of flux in a tube like
this would produce a magnetic or an
electric field in here electric Fields
have energy and the energy density in
them depends on the field the energy
density along this long tube of flux
would be
uniform
if the number of flux lines passing
through this little area is the same as
number of passing through this little
area and so forth the field strength
would be uniform along this tube of flux
here this is in fact a property of tubes
of magnetic flux and superconductors and
so forth in
superconductors uh in superconductors
you don't have of course monopoles in
superconductors but you can have long
lines of magnetic flux and they have the
property that the magnetic field is
uniform along them and therefore the
energy density is uniform along them
that means that the energy is
proportional to their
length this is a common thing in uh in
field Theory and condensed matter
physics and a variety of different
contexts where where field
energy in a field forming a long string
is proportional to the length of the
string not the length Square it's a
different kind of string another way to
think about it is is that the string is
made up of a lot of little
particles but as you pull on it and
separate the distances here no particles
form in between so as to keep the number
of particles per unit length fixed
that's another way to think about these
long flux lines that they're uniform
along their length and as you pull them
apart more particles form to fill the
gaps then in that situation it would
also be true that the energy per unit
length would be fixed and the energy
would be proportional to the
length this is by now actually an
experimental fact about uh about hadrons
that you can spin them up you can
stretch them and they have the property
that the energy per unit length is fixed
they have a it's called the string
tension the string tension is a constant
that would not be the case in an
ordinary hooks law if you stretch them
but that but this is the picture in the
rest frame in the rest frame the energy
of the string is proportional to its
length in
the infinite momentum frame where the
physics is all non-relativistic the
energy is proportional to the square of
the length like Hook's
law so these two kinds of strings hooks
law and flux
tube
are related to each
other some sense they're just the same
object being described in two different
reference frames one at rest and one
uh if you had an ordinary rubber band
and it was vibrating in with almost
relativistic speeds in one no no no wa
ordinary rubber bands if they vibrate
with relativistic speed we haven't got
the vaguest idea how to describe them we
don't want to do that no uh We've we've
we've made an indirect deduction we've
made an indirect deduction first first
half of the deduction was in the
infinite momentum frame everything is
non relativistic at least in two
Dimensions we use that to discover the
fact that the stretched energy of a
string which is L squared because it's
described nonrelativistically like a
hooks law like a hooks Law Spring is L
squar that is to be related to
m^2 indirectly from that we conclude
that if we in the rest frame the energy
of the string would be proportional to
its
length and that's interesting because
there's a wide variety of interesting uh
string-like objects that occur in field
Theory uh not made out of atoms but made
out of field uh field configurations
which have exactly the same
property
um all right let's uh let's come back in
a few minutes
it's I think uh I think I probably
exhausted uh your attention for today
but let me well let me summarize let me
summarize let me
summarize experimental properties of uh
of hadrons indicated this kind of
uh excitations along a
line had we been smart at the time we
probably would have realized that this
pattern here is the appropriate pattern
for Strings whose potential energy is
proportional to their length that's
something we actually could have deduced
directly from here that in fact why am I
saying we could have I did uh that uh
that the energy grew as the length of
such a
string that was the consequence of uh of
this relationship here all right that
was one fact next fact non-relative or
relativistic physics in a frame in which
everything is moving fast is the same as
non-relativistic physics except in one
less
Dimension uh in one less
Dimension and so we can try to build a
simple theory
of relativistic strings by going to such
a frame and just using non-relativistic
physics but in one less Dimension here
it is here's the non-relativistic string
in two-dimensional
space the only only thing we have to
remember is that wherever we saw energy
we have to think of it or internal
energy in particular internal energy
should be really identified with the
square of the mass not the
mass okay that if you remember came from
the two different expansions if you like
one of them was an
expansion in which this was the big
term and then the whole thing is
approximately of Order MC squ square
root of this thing in here the other
expansion was a term in which this was
big and then the excess energy was
proportional to M2 not M so when you do
that and you go through this little
exercise your conclusion is that the
hooks law energy of the effective
non-relativistic string should be
identified with a mass squared which
indirectly tells you that the that the
rest mass of the string is proportional
to its length and finally there are lots
and lots of field Theory and condensed
matter systems which have the same
property so that was uh something
encouraging if you
like okay let's take a rest and uh then
we can come back and either ask some
questions or I don't think I'll discuss
the quantization of the string today the
quantization is is easy we've done most
of the things that are necessary to to
figure it out it's just a collection of
harm IC
oscillators
um but uh I think we can take a rest
first just to help my comprehension
here it seems you start with a classic
string then you you you boost the hell
out of it in the in the Z Direction you
basically do a lower Str for you you get
the same physics when you go back
shouldn't you you get back to the
physics that you started with you
do you do it's just easier this way no
but you don't have the same
physics at first started with a string
that had a a length proportional uh to
its mass square in both cases in both
cases the mass is proportional to the
length and the mass squared is
proportional to the length squared in
both
cases but in one case you call the
energy the mass in the other case you
call the energy the mass square let's go
through that I I'll come back to your
question in a minute let me just go
through it again because there was some
slight of hand there was some uh tricky
business there we wrote that energy is
equal to Square t of P ^2 + m^2
okay let's uh for the moment uh forget
the motion in the XY plane let's just
concentrate on the Z Direction and The
Time Direction energy is related to time
p is the related to space there's two
ways I could expand this one of them is
good with when p is small and M is
large all right in other words when I'm
in a and when the particle is moving
slowly in my frame of reference in that
case let's see what what we do then we
write that this is equal to P * the
square < TK of 1 + m^2 over p^2
right sorry I sorry I I want to start in
the situation where p is small and M is
large good p is small and M is large so
I write this then as m^2 * 1 + P ^2 /
m^2 p is
small and M is large so p^2 over m^2 is
a small
quantity okay
nod good okay the M can come out and
this becomes M * the sare < TK of 1 + P2
+ m^2 but that's approximately 1 + p^2 /
m okay
squared which is equal to M which really
means mc^
2 plus P ^2 over 2
m so in
that context the internal energy when
the particle is at rest in space is
proportional to the mass that's your
good old e equal mc^ 2 okay and that
tells you that for a particle at rest
its inertia a particle at rest its
inertia in other words its usual
resistance to uh to
acceleration uh is the same as its mass
and its energy it's Mass meaning inertia
and its energy are proportional to each
other okay
now let's do the other expansion the
other expansion we boost like hell so
that the momentum is very
large okay and then we expand it in the
other way let's see p is very large now
so this is the square otk of p^ 2 * 1 +
m^2 over p ^
2 which is
p
plus did I do that right yeah p
plus m^2 I think over 2
p all right now this is the momentum
along the direction that we did the
Boost there are two other directions of
momentum and we could put them in
here but uh
notice that the energy apart from this
fact this piece which is just total
momentum which we can drop because it
drops out of all interesting things is
proportional to the square of the
mass so in this form the energy is
proportional to the square of the mass
and what that
says is that if a particle or a system
system of particles is moving down the
axis with an enormous momentum that its
inertia that its inertia relative to
this direction
here uh well let me let me go back let
me go back let me put in here the other
terms plus PX 2 + py^
2 they just went together with M2 this
was pz ^2 + m^2 plus px2 plus P y^2
we're taking this to be small and pz to
be large okay one of the things that
this
says is that the
inertia is now not the mass of the
particle it's the momentum along the
z-axis and that actually makes a lot of
sense the it's not true
nonrelativistically but relativistically
it is true that a given Force
perpendicular to the direction of motion
will produce a smaller acceleration the
larger the uh the larger the momentum so
this that's the first thing this P here
is the
inertia and the m s is playing the role
of an internal energy or M2 over 2 p is
playing the role of an internal energy
so internal energy becomes Mass squared
in this Frame and inertia just
becomes
pz oops that doesn't look good but
uh all right now somebody asked me about
the
connection between these kind of strings
which have this property of uh having a
energy per unit length and
superconductors I I think I mentioned it
as we were talking I will spell it
out superconductors have the property of
repelling a magnetic
field they repel they don't want to
accept magnetic field penetrating
through them they actually repel the
magnetic
field uh because they repel the magnetic
field it's kind of a pressure that is
pushing magnetic field out of the way
but if you somehow push a magnetic field
I'm going to tell you how to do that in
a minute if you push a magnetic field
into the uh into the superconductor in
such a way that the lines of force are
passing from one side of the condu super
here's a big piece of
superconductor lines of force are
passing through it like that what it
will do will be to squeeze we push those
lines of force out of the way and push
them into a uh into a
[Music]
narrow string like thing like
that that's a called a fluxoid it's
called a fluxoid or a superconducting
flux
line superconducting yeah superc
conducting flux line magnetic flux not
electric flux magnetic flux and how can
you make one in principle in a uh in a
uh in a superconductor here's what you
might do I doubt very much well this is
probably not the way it's done in in
really but uh you take a p piece of
superconductor you drill an incredibly
narrow hole through it this is a gunan
experiment this is not something uh that
I want you to go away with it's a
practical experiment you drill through
it an incredibly small uh uh
um let's see am I going to get this
right ah before you pull before you cool
down the superconductor before you cool
down the super conductor you take a long
bar magnet and you stick it through the
hole like that flux lines come out this
way from the bar
magnet and this
way now you cool it down so it becomes a
superconductor and you draw out the
magnet these lines of flux here will get
pulled into the
magnet even after you've pulled out the
magnet lines of flux will go through
that magnet and they will form a thin
tube through that
magnet the field along the tube will be
uniform and because the field is uniform
that means the energy per unit length is
fixed okay now let's go a little bit
further imagine that we had magnetic
monopoles we can actually simulate
magnetic monopoles but let's suppose we
really did have magnetic monopoles that
they really were magnetic monopoles in
the
world and they may well be but we
haven't discovered them
yet but let's suppose we had discovered
them and we could manipulate
them okay then we could take a monopole
and an antim monopole put them right on
top of each other don't let them
annihilate keep them a little bit
apart uh take them and put them into the
superconductor
monopole and anti monopole I'm not going
to tell you which which one is which I'm
just going to draw two of them and of
course the monopole and the anti
monopole have some flux lines between
them now cool down the
superconductor and take the monopole and
the antim monopole and start to separate
them what
happens exactly the same thing that we
think happens between a pair of
quirks except that this is just an
ordinary magnetic field between the
monopole and and antim monopole so
inside a superconductor a monopole and
an antim monopole would have an energy
which would be proportional to the
distance between them why the distance
between them because the string between
them has a uh an energy proportional to
its
length Okay the monopole and the antim
monopole could not separate from each
other they would be confined because as
you start to separate them the energy
goes up with the length and uh and
that's the uh that's the Char
of what
happens to uh to hadrons or quirks and a
hron you separate them and their energy
goes up so okay so this is a system for
the energy is proportional to the
length and uh it has the characteristics
of the same kind of string does that
answer your question whoever asked
me I don't know who asked me oh well I
guess he's gone
[Applause]
the question was uh what's what's taking
the role of a superf fluid for the Huns
what is the super the super conducting
fluid virtual
monopoles that's what it's thought to be
virtual monopoles but not these
different monopoles chromodynamic
[Music]
monopoles
uh in the super super conductor here the
condensate the superconducting
condensate is made out of electric
charge and it causes confinement of
magnetic
charge in Quantum
chromodynamics quirks are confined and
they are kind of the electric charges of
uh of quantum
chromodynamics the things which condense
our magnetic
charges uh you say where are those
magnetic charges why don't we see them
because they're always condensed in the
vacuum so but this is this is beyond uh
uh what I had intended to talk about
today okay what other questions uh come
up oh it's almost 9 o00 okay yeah so the
energy being proportional to the length
is the rule for highly relativistic well
a superconductor is not a highly
relativist it's it's a we talk about
string it's no no but it's string like
but so if you took a uh a regular hooks
law string made of Springs and had it
going relativistically inside break
apart that's all assuming you
could you have to make up some Theory I
don't know you have to make up some
Theory but that that construction would
then have an energy proportional to its
life I don't know what it would do
depends on the details no uh there's
something special about energy that
grows link as I said what it really
means in particle language is that as
you
separate the constituents of the
string as you pull it
apart the energy of pulling it apart
instead of just separating and making
larger distances makes
more makes more particles so that the so
that the density of them along the
string always stays the same that's the
character of uh of these kind of
strings and the other way to think about
it is there are strings made up at a
field where because field lines are not
allowed to end field lines are not
allowed to end as long as the field
doesn't spread out this way it has to
remain uniform in the other
direction so it's uh a characteristic of
flux lines uh flux lines which are
confined to a
tube if you had any kind of situation
where an electric field were confined
and prevented from spreading out in the
perpendicular
Direction the energy per unit length of
it would be uh constant yeah what about
the kind of residual motion along the pz
direction along the Ah that's a very
good question yeah
remarkably the way String Theory works
is there are not independent degrees of
freedom for motion along the other
direction this is a remarkable and
strange fact that in string theory you
do not include directly degrees of
freedom for the motion of the string
along the direction of the uh the Boost
here it is thought that that's connected
with something called the holographic
principle that really in a gravitating
system you need one less direct
Dimension to describe it but it's one of
the very remarkable features of string
theory that you don't describe the
string in let's say in three-dimensional
space you in this limit you describe it
only by the two-dimensional motion and
yet as we will see it's consistent with
uh with uh lorensen variance yeah how
many how many data points do we have on
the Reggie plot five or 10 or I don't
know what the maximum number number is
now uh I don't know seven something like
that it's a it's not endless uh but uh
doesn't give any evidence of uh of
giving
out I'll come I'll talk about it another
time but uh the the evidence for that
but remember that we're not really
interested in hadron so I was just
giving you a historical uh perspective
of where the whole thing came from
um but now we want to St study this
mathematical Theory and not insist that
it looks like hadrons but just ask what
it does look like and what we'll find
out is that it looks more like gravity
than it does uh
hyrons um what if it was a elect what if
it was something that is what if what
was an
electronic well the the the idea that we
had kind some kind of spatial element of
the particle the composit of the
particle for a particle that doesn't
seem to be composite
well okay let's let's be all right so
the question is can be expressed in two
different ways let's see um
uh it can be expressed or the answer to
your question can be expressed in terms
of the smallness of the particle or in
terms of the energy that it takes to
increase the particle by one unit all
right so let's let's do you remember the
formula for the energy of a rotating
system is a function of its angular
momentum
L2 where that's the angular momentum
divid 2 * something remember what it is
moment of
inertia and what's the moment of inertia
related
to the mass the mass and the square of
the size of the system right
the m r s not M2 r s m r 2 but the point
is that for a given m M the moment of
inertia gets smaller and smaller as a
system
gets sorry yes the moment of inertia
gets very small when the system is very
small now what is l l is angular
momentum and it comes in
Quant so this is proportional to
n^2 H squ or something like that and now
you can ask how much energy does it take
to go from Nal 0 to Nal
1 n equals z the energy it might be a
little bit of energy but the energy this
piece of the energy is
zero the first excited state would have
an energy hr^ s over 2 * 1 / by the
moment of
inertia and if the object is very very
small the moment of inertia is very
large no one over the moment of inertia
is very
large so the excitation energy the
energy that it takes to increase
the angular momentum by one unit becomes
very very big if the object is small
well hadrons are big objects they have
small moments of inertia on the on on
the scale of uh quantum gravity hyrons
are just enormous I mean they're they're
you know they're big blobs they have
large moments of inertia the energy
taken to excite one is not very big
electrons are known to be much
smaller the expectation is that they're
exceedingly small maybe 10 to the 16th
times smaller than a proton you square
their radius to get the moment of
inertia so that could mean 10 32 times
smaller moment of inertia and that means
that the energy of excitation would be
10 the 32 times bigger well maybe that's
that's that's probably too much but uh
so if electrons have excited States
because they're so small if they have
rotational
excitations those rotational
excitations well I think I lost my true
frouchy plot but the mass necessary to
increase the angular momentum by one
unit would be way off on the no that end
of the of the
plot just too much it just takes too
much energy to spin it up when I say too
much I mean too much compared to the
energies that are available in particle
collisions okay so the energy needed uh
to excite a hyron by one
unit is less is roughly of order of gev
you Collide particles at a gev or
whatever it is you see these
excitations The energy needed to to spin
up an
electron is very much higher you don't
see them how about the energy needed to
spin up a uh a
um a basketball by one unit of angular
momentum
very small very small in fact you can't
even see that it's
quantized right so an atom it'
be uh okay whatever it is first you know
a couple of electron volts you mean to
spin up an atom by one
unit couple of electron
volts good
okay for more please visit us at
stanford.edu